George Gaylord Simpson Papers 1918-1984 Mss.Ms.Coll.31
American Philosophical Society
- George Gaylord Simpson Papers
  - Series VII. Students' Papers, 1960-1967; 1.5 linear feet (Box 99-101)
    - Allen, Garland E. (The evolution of biochemical novelties), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Auerbach, Judith (Morgan revisited), 1966 (Box 99)
    - Baskin, Jonathan N. (The concept of preadaptation), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Beatty, Joseph A. (The problem of ant-mimicry in spiders), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Boss, Kenneth J. (Sexual selection), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Brady, Allen R. (New structures in the arthropods), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Bush, Guy L. (Sympathetic speciation), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Carroll, Robert (Emergence of new structures), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Coles, Richard W. (Evolution in closed Drosophila populations), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Colwell, Robert K. (The mosquito fauna of the Egyptian oases), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Curtin, Patrick (Origins of the alpine flora of the Sierra Nevada), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Dethlefsen, E.S. (Behavior and human evolution), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Foster, Merrill W. (A preliminary investigation into the zoogeography of two groups of marine invertebrates), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Friedlaender, Jonathan S. (Determinants of evolutionary rates), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Gates, Elizabeth (Ecological factors in speciation), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Greer, Allen E. (Protective and warning coloration in elapid snakes), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Grobman, Alexander (Evolutionary role of heterosis), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Grobstein, Paul (The group selection problem), 1966 (Box 99)
    - Gurn, Paul H. (Considerations on the Ethiopian avifauna), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Guthrie, Daniel A. (The interpretation of resemblances), 1960 (Box 99)
    - Hackner, Betty (Distribution patterns in Rhizophora and their significance for zoogeography), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Haedrich, Richard L. (The adaptations of pelagic and bathypelagic fish), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Haedrich, Richard L. (The Sargasso Sea as a faunal region), 1963 (Box 99)
    - Hodge, Jonathan (The theory of natural selection), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Holden, John (Up Noah's gangplank), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Horn, David J. (The zoogeography of caues), 1965 (Box 99)
    - Hunt, George L. (Reproductive strategies in the animal kingdom), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Jenkins, Robert (Phenotypic plasticity in animals), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Jones, Margaret A. (Polymorphism, predator behavior and protective coloration), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Katona, Steven K. (Speciation in the zooplankton), 1966 (Box 99)
    - Kenk, Vida Carmen (Adaptive geographic variation and clines), 1962 (Box 99)
    - Kerfoot, William B. (The evolution and degradation of the third eye), 1967 (Box 99)
    - Konner, Melvin J. (Trends and modes of change in the evolution of vertebrate behavior), ca. 1966 (Box 99)
    - Lazell, J., Jr. (The Simpsonian concept of evolutionary role), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Lipkin, Mack (On the ontogeny and phylogeny of proteins), 1964 (Box 99)
    - Lloyd, D.G. (The evolution of adaptive modifications), 1960 (Box 99)
    - MacLeod, Roy M. (Comparative method in biological thought), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Maglio, Vincent J. (Differential rates in evolution), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Marshall, John K. (Instinct and animal behavior), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Mayer, Garry F. (Speciation and adaptation in the Hadal zone), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Menezes, Naercio A. (Evolutionary role of mutation in microorganisms and higher organisms), 1964 (Box 100)
    - Menezes, Naercio A. (The zoogeographical significance of the Amazon River system), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Middleton, Richard B. (The evolution of sexuality), 1960 (Box 100)
    - Mills, Norman (The effects of racial intermingling), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Minkoff, Eli C. (Evolutionary trends and phylogenetic laws), 1964 (Box 100)
    - Minkoff, Eli C. (Origin of the Madagascar land faunas), ca. 1965 (Box 100)
    - Mitchell, D.D. (Some proposed anti-inbreeding mechanisms), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Moxey, Carl Farr (Viviparity and the brooding habit in non-holothurian echinoderms), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Mullen, Jim (Regressive evolution), 1963 (Box 100)
    - Musick, John A. (Some aspects of macromolecules and evolution), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Neaves, William B. (Insular herpetofaunas in the gulf of California), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Odoroff, Charles L. (The distribution of the genus Nothofagus), 1963 (Box 100)
    - Oliver, Charles G. (Relict subarctic faunas as reflected in three butterfly genera), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Porter, Charles C. (Speciation and species structure), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Porter, Duncan M. (Ecotypic variation in plants), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Pringle, John R. (Faunal resemblance), 1963 (Box 100)
    - Reichardt, Hans (Carabidae (Coleoptera) in the Mexican transition zone), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Reiskind, Jonathan (Zoogeography and the higher taxa of the ants), 1963 (Box 100)
    - Richard, Emily L. (Mimicry, a problem in evolution), 1960 (Box 100)
    - Rubinoff, Ira (Barriers in the sea and their effect upon speciation), 1960 (Box 100)
    - Salk, Peter (The function of the genetic material in higher organisms), 1965 (Box 100)
    - Saunders, Jeffrey J. and Thomas R. VanDevender (Report on second trip to Ojo del Galeana, Chihuahua, Mexico), 1973 (Box 100)
    - Sawyer, Janet M. (Kin selection and the evolution of altruism), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Schanfield, M.S. (Population structure and evolution), 1966 (Box 100)
    - Schoener, Thomas W. (Avifaunal tropical diversity), 1963 (Box 100)
    - Schwartzkopf, Gary W. (Evolutionary role of mutation in microorganisms and higher organisms), 1962 (Box 100)
    - Shapiro, Bert (Some aspects of pulmonate zoogeography), ca. 1963 (Box 101)
    - Sill, William (General zoogeographic relationships of the Mesozoic and Cenozoic crocodilia), 1965 (Box 101)
    - Simberloff, Daniel (Speciation and host specificity among parasitic insects), 1964 (Box 101)
    - Simpson, Beryl (Geographical distribution of vultures), 1963 (Box 101)
    - Smith, Roy Edgar (Cryptic coloration and warning coloration), 1962 (Box 101)
    - Stokes, Glenn M. (Polytypic species, isolates and speciation), 1962 (Box 101)
    - Stokes, Glenn M. (Prolegommena to Australian entomogeography), 1963 (Box 101)
    - Stuardo, Jose (Marine faunistic divisions of southern South America), 1965 (Box 101)
    - Stuardo, Jose (Role of some ecological factors in the evolution of the deep-sea benthic fauna), 1965 (Box 101)
  - Series VIII. Travel Journals, 1924-1984; 1 linear ft. (Box 102-103)
    Typed carbon copies of journals written by the Simpsons on their numerous trips, and are arranged alphabetically by place name. This series does not include field notes from expeditions. (See Series IV for field notes.) Of note in this series is Anne Roe Simpson's "Note on travel diaries," which describes the journals. (See folder listing on page 33.) Not individually cataloged.
  - Series IX. Biographical Materials, 0.5 linear ft. (Box 104)
    Miscellaneous papers and documents pertaining to Simpson's life and work. Most of these materials were written by Simpson. Of note in this series are Simpson's autobiographical notes, which cover events and thoughts on his life not found elsewhere, and his remarks on research and publications, which details the progression of his work. (See folder listing on page 35.) Not individually cataloged.
  - Series X. Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1.5 linear ft. (Box 105-107)
    Certificates, plaques, and medals pertaining to Simpson's honorary degrees, memberships, fellowships, and awards. These materials are broken down by form. Box A contains encased certificates; Box B contains plaques and oversized certificates; and Box C contains certificates and papers in file folders. (See folder listing on page 36.) Not individually cataloged.
  - Series XI. Photographs, ca.1920-1984; 8 linear ft. (Box 108-118)
    Slides, negatives, rolls of film, lantern slides, and photos pertaining chiefly to Simpson, his family, and his early expeditions. This series contains approximately 1,500 slides covering a variety of subjects, from flowers to rodeos to expedition sites to the Simpson's New Mexico home, Los Pinavetes. Photographs concerning expeditions and travel include Venezuela (1,060 photos), Patagonia (240 photos), Brazil (70 photos), New Mexico (110 photos), Florida (30 photos), and China and Japan (11 photos).
    Of special note in this series are the 1,060 photos of Simpson's 1938-1939 trip to Venezuela. Also included are five indexes (bound volumes) to Simpson's Patagonia and Venezuela photos, and five rough books containing notes and sketches, also taken while in Patagonia and Venezuela. Finally, many of the lantern slides in this collection appear to be associated with Simpson's lecture presentations.
    Not individually cataloged. The following represents a sample of the photographs available in the collection.
    - George Gaylord Simpson, preparing to leave a fossile dig., ca. 1930; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length profile view of Simpson, in desert, with packs, holding pick axe.
    - George Gayrlord Simpson at Camp Number Two., ca. 1930; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of desert camp, automobile in foreground, Simpson, standing at entrance of tent, in distance.
    - George Gaylord Simpson and others at the sea-cow pond., ca. 1940; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of six people, including Simpson, leaning on railing, trees in background.
      Handwritten note on back of photograph: "L to R: Smith, Smith, Barenburg [?], Williams, Simpson, Williams, at sea-cow pond, Permanina [?]."
    - George Gaylord Simpson sitting with unidentified man and woman., ca. 1950; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of Simpson, reading a book, sitting outside in wooden chair, along with unidentified man and woman.
    - George Gaylord Simpson, sitting in study at National Museum of Natural History., ca. 1955; 1.0 Photograph(s); Simpson, sitting in front of bookshelf, framed photographs in background.
    - Crowd outside of Casa Rosada, after the revolution, Buenos Aires, Argentina., 1955; 1.0 Photograph(s); Crowd view with men and women walking, Casa Rosada in background.
    - George Gaylord Simpson and unidentified man, standing outside., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Simpson and unidentified man, standing outside, buildings and statue in background.
    - George Simpson, bust length portrait, while at University of Arizona., ca. 1890; 1.0 Photograph(s); Portrait of Simpson, wearing glasses.
  - Series XII. Miscellaneous, 0.5 linear ft. (Box 119)
    Financial records, research proposals, Venezuelan materials, Simpson's notes on the Arabic language, American Museum of Natural History materials, and newspaper clippings. (See folder listing on page 39.) Not individually cataloged.
  - Unprocessed materials
    Compiled by Joe Cain (J.Cain@ucl.ac.uk), 04/22/99
    Unprocessed collection, literal folder titles only. No content descriptions
    - [Travel Diaries] 1970-74 Originals, carbons, miscellany (Box Unprocessed-1)
      - Seychelles 1970 Original and miscellany carbon (Folder 1)
      - Antarctica 1971 Journal and carbon (Folder 2)
      - Antarctica 1971 Miscellany (Folder 3)
      - Argentina-Antarctica 1972 Original no carbon (Folder 4)
      - Yucatan-Galapagos 1973 Original and Carbon (Folder 5)
      - Miscellany, 1972-3 (Folder 6)
      - Africa 1972 Journal, Carbon and Miscellany (Folder 7)
      - Stella Salaris 1973 no journal (Folder 8)
        [cruise line brochure]
      - and Antarctic 1970 Original and Miscellany no carbon (Folder 9)
      - Arctic 1974 Original and Carbon (Folder 10)
    - [Travel Diaries], 1951-68 (Box Unprocessed-2)
      - Australia and Around the World, 1951 (Folder 1)
      - Brazil, 1954-1955 (Folder 2)
        [GGS and ARS on trip 8 Oct 54 - 20 Feb 55]
      - Africa 1961 Maps, stratigraphy, photos, specimens, journal (Folder 3)
      - Around Africa 1967 Original and Carbon (Folder 4)
      - Europe 1960 2nd top copy (Folder 5)
      - Europe 1960 original and carbon (Folder 6)
      - Brazil 1956 Carbon and Original (Folder 7)
        [leave 28 May 56
      - Africa 1961 2nd top copy, 2 carbons (Folder 8)
      - Australia and New Zealand 1968 Original and Carbon (Folder 9)
    - [Travel Diaries], 1975-77 (Box Unprocessed-3)
      - Indonesia, 1975 (Folder 1)
      - Artic 1974 Miscellany (Folder 2)
      - North Cape Original, maps, 1975 (Folder 3)
      - "North Cape" '75 (Folder 4)
      - Coral Sea-1976 Original and Carbon (Folder 5)
      - Himalayas 1977 Original and Carbon (Folder 6)
      - Moscow and the Adriatic 1977 Original (Folder 7)
      - South Pacific, 1977 (Folder 8)
    - GGS + ARS Journals Venezuela 1938-39 originals and carbons (Box Unprocessed-4)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 Rough, partial typescript (Folder 1)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 pp. 1-428 (Folder 2)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 pp. 429-694 (Folder 3)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 Notes and Supplement (Folder 4)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 Carbon pp. 1-188 2nd partial top copy 1-155 (Folder 5)
      - Venezuela 1938-39 Carbon pp. 394- (Folder 6)
        [some of this is on microfilm already and duplicates stuff in MS31 series 8.
    - [Travel Diaries, etc.], 1978-81 (Box Unprocessed-5)
      - For Trip, 1978 (Folder 1)
        [includes photos and journal beginning 20 Aug 1978 - 30 Nov includes China, Japan and Pacific]
      - Pacific Circle, 1978 (Folder 2)
      - Alaska brochure (Folder 3)
        [not in a folder]
      - Magnificent Odyssey (Folder 4)
      - Athens to CuracC#o, Nov 18 - Dec 21, 1979 (Folder 5)
      - England (Folder 6)
      - China (Folder 7)
      - Buenos Aires, La Plata, Santa Mariana, 1981 (Folder 8)
    - Journal Originals, 1924-1936 (Box Unprocessed-6)
      - Original 1924 Texas Panhandle (Folder 1)
      - Patagonia, (1930-1931) (Folder 2)
        [several folders]
      - Patagonia 1933-34 Original (Folder 3)
      - Patagonia and Russia 1933-34 Carbon (Folder 4)
      - Montana, 1935 (Folder 5)
      - Western Reconnaissance, 1936 (Folder 6)
      - San Juan Basin, 1948 (Folder 7)
    - Travel Diaries Typescripts, 1938-39, 1951 (Box Unprocessed-7)
      - Venezuelan Journal pp 502-570, plus Notes on Venezuelan Journal 33 pp. Includes maps of Gran Sabana and a couple of photos (Folder 1)
      - The Venezuelan Journal 1938-1939 pages 1-278 George Gaylord Simpson (Folder 2)
      - Yellow binder: pp. 100-200 of Venezuelan Journal] (Folder 3)
      - Black binder: pp. 201-299 of Venezuelan Journal (Folder 4)
      - Cream binder: pp. 300-399 of Venezuelan Journal (Folder 5)
      - Red binder: 400-501 of Venezuelan Journal (Folder 6)
      - Binder: Australia and Around the World 1951 typescript (Folder 7)
    - Travel Diaries Typescripts, 1954-1970 (Box Unprocessed-8)
      - Blue Binder: Brazil [label falling off], pp. 103-208 typescript, 1954-1955 (Folder 1)
      - Red binder 1956 Journal Amazon Basin typescript (Folder 2)
      - Binder: Europe, 1960 (Folder 3)
      - Binder: East Africa, Greece, Italy, 1961 (Folder 4)
      - Binder: Around Africa 1967 Australia and New Zealand, 1968 (Folder 5)
      - Binder: Parts South: Argentina and Antarctica and Parts East: The Seychelles (Folder 6)
    - Travel Diaries Typescripts, 1971-1980 (Box Unprocessed-9)
      All typescripts in binders
      - Binder: Argentina and Antarctica, 1971 and 1972 (Folder 1)
      - Binder: Africa Yucatan and the Galapagos The Arctic, 1972, 1973, 1974 (Folder 2)
      - Binder: North Cape Cruise, 1975 (Folder 3)
      - Binder: Coral Sea Cruise, 1976 (Folder 4)
      - Binder: Isles of the Orient Seas, 1975 (Folder 5)
      - Binder: Darjeeling and Around the World, 1977 (Folder 6)
      - Binder: South Pacific Cruise, 1977 (Folder 7)
      - Binder: Moscow and the Adriatic, 1977 (Folder 8)
      - Binder: Pacific Circle, 1978 (Folder 9)
      - Binder: People's Republic of China and Japan, 1980 (Folder 10)
    - Travel Diaries Transcripts 1979-1984 Books, misc (Box Unprocessed-10)
      - Binder: The Magnificent Odessy: Athens to CuracC#o England Buenos Aires, La Plata, Santa Mariana, November 21 to December 18, 1979; 1980; 1981 (Folder 1)
      - Binder: Baja, California Los Angeles San Juan-Los Angeles Around South America, 1981; 1982, 1983 (Folder 2)
      - Notebook:, 16 April 1984- 22-26 May (Folder 3)
        [for Singapore includes Anne's handwriting. George dies shortly hereafter.
      - Book: Francis Stehli and S David Webb (eds.). The Great American Biotic Interchange., 1985 (Folder 4)
        [Simpson Feschrift]
      - Book: Kathryn M. Flanagan and Jason Lillegraven (eds). Vertebrates Phylogeny and Philosophy. Simpson Feschrift, 1986 (Folder 5)
      - Award from U Arizona for George (Folder 6)
    - Anne Roe Simpson, Biographical Materials, Painters Summaries, Rorschach Protocol (Box Unprocessed-11)
      - Personal History (Dictated) (Folder 1)
      - Honors (Folder 2)
      - Personal History (Folder 3)
      - Painters Summaries (Folder 4)
        [in big envelope.]
- Simspon-Eastlake Papers, 1918-1975; 0.5 linear feet
  The bulk of the Simpson-Eastlake Collection is comprised of personal correspondence written by George Gaylord Simpson to his sister, Martha Lee Simpson Eastlake, and to his parents Joseph Alexander Simpson and Julia Kinney Simpson. In addition to providing some details on Simpson's personal life, the letters include sporadic information on his scientific expeditions, particularly those to South American during the 1930s.
  The collection has been enhanced with the addition of some autobiographical essays by Simpson written in 1933, 1954, and the 1970s, and an extensive typescript rumination by Simpson on his research and publications.
  - Box 1, 1918-1932; 68 ALsS
  - Box 2, 1933-1975; 72 ALsS
    - Remarks on Research and Publications, August 11, 1975; 87p.; Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984
    - Autobiographical notes, 1975; 6p.; Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984
    - Autobiographical notes, 1933, 1954, 1970, 1974; ca.150p.; Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984